<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Egel's Blog</title><link href="http://egel.pl/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://egel.pl/feeds/tag/console.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://egel.pl/</id><updated>2016-09-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>Being a perpetrator of DOS attack</title><link href="http://egel.pl/being-a-perpetrator-of-dos-attack.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-09-21T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Maciej Sypień</name></author><id>tag:egel.pl,2016-09-21:being-a-perpetrator-of-dos-attack.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Few days ago my tiny VPS server has become an attacker of denial of service. Really?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was mailed by automatic DO mailer, that my server have become an attacker of denial of service and everything have been shutdown.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hi there,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've detected an outgoing Denial of Service attack (http://do.co/21Y1Gc1) originating from your Droplet. Due to the traffic’s harmful nature, your Droplet was taken offline; this means it is not connected to the internet and all hosted sites and services are unreachable. We know that this action is disruptive, but it’s necessary to protect you, our network, and the target of your Droplet’s attack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can access your droplet using this console link: &lt;em&gt;CUT LINK&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because this means your Droplet has been compromised, you’ll need to back up your data and transfer it to a new Droplet. We have a recovery tool to assist you, but any databases on your Droplet will need to be backed up before we boot your Droplet into the recovery tool because you won’t be able to make the backups afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Specific backup steps vary depending on the database software in use, which is most commonly MySQL. If you’re not sure how, http://do.co/1h0uWgm will show you how to back up your databases from MySQL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have finished backing up your data, the next step is downloading and transferring your data to your new Droplet. Please update this ticket when you’re ready and we’ll configure this Droplet so you can proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve enabled our backup service or have a snapshot of the Droplet, you can restore directly from that image instead of going through the recovery process. Be aware that this will destroy any changes or additions made to the Droplet since the creation date of the image you use to restore from.  If you do this, please update the ticket as we will need to reconfigure networking to get your Droplet back online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don’t need the data from this Droplet, you can destroy this Droplet at your convenience.  If you’d like to keep the current IP address, you will need to use our rebuild function. This acts like a clean install of your OS and is currently the only way to ensure you retain your IP.  As with restoring from an image, please let us know once you’ve done this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any further questions, or if we can further assist, please let us know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regards,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Trust &amp;amp; Safety
DigitalOcean Support&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please login to view the ticket:
https://&lt;DO I will not sponsor your links!&gt;/support/tickets&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks so much,
DigitalOcean&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was very surprising for me, because I only use this VPS displaying my blog and as a web development sandbox (basic stuff like: Apache, Nginx, PostgeSQL, MySQL, ect.). Nothing harmful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I lend the cheapest server they've got, 512MB RAM, 1 Core CPU around 2.2GHz with 20GB storage just for having fun with creating something awesome and share it with the community (also with you).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the latest time when I use DO VPS I've try to setup private Gitlab on this tiny machine and I was succeeded. I setup Gitlab + Apache + MySQL (and couple of other deamons) and this works flawlessly with additional drive SWAP around 2GB. But after few days my server has been shutdown instantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So when the super scripts of DO discovered, that my little server generate bigger traffic (guessing this), then my server has been cut out from connection to the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even after shutting down my VPS, I was still charged with full amount - it was not much, but hey, I hire this VPS mainly to have a cheap server with connection to the Internet! If I want a simple server with similar amount of RAM, I would buy Raspberry PI and connect only to a power adapter without accessing to Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was really angry about this situation, but in the end that's good, that this happen to me - I change VPS provider much quicker then I thought :)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="linux"></category><category term="console"></category><category term="server"></category></entry><entry><title>Install the latest nVidia drivers for Linux</title><link href="http://egel.pl/install-the-latest-nvidia-drivers-for-linux.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-11-02T00:00:00+01:00</updated><author><name>Maciej Sypień</name></author><id>tag:egel.pl,2015-11-02:install-the-latest-nvidia-drivers-for-linux.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="intro-article-image-sm"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Tmux" src="http://egel.pl/images/terminal_icon.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The time has come that I had to face with reinstall of the Nvidia driver on my Mint
17 distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, while using my distro, there appear couple of problems with "Nvidia proprietary drivers".
As a pro Linux guy (laugh),  I pressed &lt;code&gt;ctrl&lt;/code&gt;+&lt;code&gt;alt&lt;/code&gt;+&lt;code&gt;F1&lt;/code&gt;, and got a black screen with flashing cursor. YES! - I shouted immediately - the console isn't broken for good - I sad to myself in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I red somewhere, that the problem could have something with the framebuffer. So I made few modifications to &lt;code&gt;/etc/default/grub&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please remember, backup always go first!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;table class="highlighttable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo cp /etc/default/grub /etc/default/grub.bak
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now edit the grub file by entering&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="highlighttable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo vim /etc/default/grub
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While editing in your favorite editor (I choose &lt;code&gt;vim&lt;/code&gt;), uncomment the lines, simply by removing the &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt; in front of those lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If your monitor support better resolutions you can change &lt;code&gt;GRUB_GFXMODE&lt;/code&gt; for another value, my highest was &lt;code&gt;1024x768&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;table class="highlighttable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;1
2&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;GRUB_TERMINAL=console
GRUB_GFXMODE=640x480
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Save the file and run &lt;code&gt;update-grub&lt;/code&gt; to implement the changes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="highlighttable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo update-grub
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I had to resolve which display manager do I have on my Mint?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="highlighttable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;1&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;cat /etc/X11/default-display-manager
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my case, it was &lt;code&gt;mdm&lt;/code&gt;, so then I stopped display manager, installed drivers and enabled display manager again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="highlighttable"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="linenos"&gt;&lt;div class="linenodiv"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;1
2
3
4&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td class="code"&gt;&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;sudo service mdm stop
chmod +x /path/to/downloaded/driver/NVIDIA-Linux-x86_64-*.run
sudo sh /path/to/downloaded/driver/NVIDIA-Linux-x86_64-*.run
sudo service mdm start
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That's it. After pressing &lt;code&gt;Alt&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;Ctrl&lt;/code&gt; + &lt;code&gt;F8&lt;/code&gt; the graphical interface showed up as well as a smile on my face :)&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="linux"></category><category term="terminal"></category><category term="console"></category></entry></feed>